## **MATTHEW SPENCER**

<u>matt@mattspencer.net</u> - +64 022 071 3499 – Wellington, NZ Linkedin.com/in/mmspencer - Authorized to work in NZ and US

# LEAD DATA SCIENTIST and SOLUTION ARCHITECT

Driven to unlock insights in large complex data sets and to deliver solutions to business needs. Proven leader, customer advocate, and forward thinker with 20 years of technical experience. TEDx nominated, Top Secret Cleared, and possessing a Masters of Science in Business Data Analytics. Seeking data analysis and technical leadership roles as well as a culture of innovation and learning.

R - Data Management - Solution Architecture - Strategy - Technical Roadmaps Statistical Analysis - Clustering - Machine Learning - Data Mining - Team Leadership

#### MOST RELATED PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# LEIDOS (Morgantown, WV) Nov 2018 – PRESENT

Lead Data Scientist and Software Solution Architect

Built and lead a team of Data Scientists and Data Engineers to tackle Data Science problems and implement commercial healthcare solutions. Led projects involving real-time data processing, clustering, and entity resolution.

#### DATA DRIVEN WV (Morgantown, WV) Sep 2017 – PRESENT

Founder, Data Scientist, Board Member, Mentor

Created organization of Data Scientists to tackle non-profit, small business, state, and local problems in a data driven approach.

### FBI (Clarksburg, WV) Oct 2015 – Nov 2018

IT Roadmap Lead, Enterprise and Solutions Architect, Data Science SME Data Analytics, Software Development and Architecture, Strategic Technical Planning, Oracle Database Administration

- Created Division model for Data Analytics
- Architect and IT Roadmap Lead for implementation of SAFe (Scaled Agile) Framework
- Author of whitepapers/presentations about Big Data and role of Data Sciences
- Part of team that implemented Crime Data Explorer utilizing 200+ new Open-Source libraries to visualize Crime Statistics in the United States. (https://crime-data-explorer.fr.cloud.gov)
- Implemented internal Open-Source framework for code, automation, CI/CD
- Completed Supervisor Development Training and formal mentor programs
- Member of NIST Big Data Public Working Group to develop Big Data Roadmap.

#### NANTUCKET DATA PLATFORM (Remote) July 2018 - Oct 2018

Data Manager and Consulting Data Scientist

Consulting data analysis for businesses and nonprofits in Nantucket Island.

# WEST VIRGINIA UNIVERSITY (Morgantown, WV) Oct 2014 - Nov 2015

Business Analyst, Lead for Enterprise Reporting

Technical/Business lead for WVU's first Scholarship Management System that changed how students apply to and are rewarded scholarships. Solution automates applications, matches scholarships, improves processes for award selection, candidate review, and recommendations. Technical/Business lead for Enterprise Reporting.

### STATE OF WISCONSIN (Madison, WI) Mar 2012 - Aug 2014

Department of Justice – Applications Architect/Technical Architect
Strategic Planning, IT Management, Technical Requirements Analysis, IT Road mapping,
Vendor Management, Life Cycle Development, Technical Project Management, Data
Modeling, SharePoint and Office 365 Architecting

- Developed DOJ's first SaaS to offer to other state Justice Depts to offer FBI integrations.
- Architected a major application rewrite from PowerBuilder system to Java/Oracle.
- Implemented LiveScan and CardScan devices to fingerprint card/scan process.
- Wrote several RFI/RFB/RFPs and served as technical procurement SME.
- Planned major rapsheet template change used by police officers across the state.
- Planned major implementation of a replacement online record check system.
- Chaired subcommittee and served as technical architect for legislative funded mandate for law enforcement to gather DNA at arrest.

\_\_\_\_\_

#### **EDUCATION**

## WEST VIRGINIA UNIVERSITY (Morgantown, WV)

M.S. Business Data Analytics (2017-2018)

Top of class and top 10% of all graduating classes, Honor Society of Phi Kappa Phi Dissertation/Capstone Research: 'Convex Clustering and Multi-View Learning on Clinical Data for Improved ACO Quality Measure Tracking.'

Co-created convex clustering package (cvxTrain) for R.

Skills/Classes/Research involving: R, Simple and Multi Linear Regression, Model Evaluation, Stat Computing, Machine Learning, Data Mining, Predictive Modeling, Spark, SQL, Regularization, Maximum Likelihood Estimation, Tableau, Convex Clustering, Shiny

### Bachelor of Arts (2009)

Self-designed degree surrounding Architectural Design.

### **VOLUNTEER PROJECTS**

### Google.org 2019

Reviewer for AI and Machine Learning (DataKind)

Helped Google.org select the most promising proposals submitted to the Google AI Impact Challenge.

#### Microsoft 2019

Ambassador for Microsoft DataKind accelerator

Selected to lead the 'Code for Miami' team to address affordability housing needs in the Miami area.

# The Good Judgment Project 2014-2015

Forecaster

Analyst predicting world changing events via aggregative contingent estimation against 17 agencies in the US intelligence community. Member of small team to hash out consensus judgments regarding geopolitics.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

Technical Reviewer for the following publications:

'Microsoft Application Virtualization Cookbook' by Packt Publishing. August 17 August 2015.

'Troubleshooting Citrix XenApp' by Packt Publishing. 29 December 2015

#### OTHER RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

**EPIC** (Madison, WI) Jun 2011 – Mar 2012

**Epic Client Systems Manager** 

Designed and implemented system platforms for Electronic Health Record software for 10+ national hospital systems, SME for Telemedicine and Microsoft App-V, Part of team to research Telemedicine as a potential Epic service.

- Successful Epic implementations at more than 10+ hospital systems from setting up development environments onsite to Go-Lives.
- Implemented Epic's first customer with Microsoft App-V and Citrix.
- Submitted several pieces of functionality for patent review.
- Trained technical staff at customer sites to build, utilize, and maintain Epic systems.
- Mentored customer staff to pass certification exams relevant to Epic systems.

Mylan (Morgantown, WV) Aug 2009 – May 2011

Messaging and Enterprise Content Management Administrator

SharePoint Architect and Infrastructure Technical Lead, Offshore Team Supervisor, Email Systems Engineer, Blackberry Enterprise Admin, Legal eDiscovery Admin Largest Success:

Planned and implemented a \$3.5M USD global deployment of SharePoint to 15,000+ users, ahead of time and under budget.

West Virginia University (Morgantown, WV) Aug 2005 – Aug 2009 Professional Technologist 3

Tier 3 Technical Support. Information Systems Technician for West Virginia University and later Robert C. Byrd Health Sciences Center.

**Point Park College (now University)** (Pittsburgh, PA) Sep 2003 – Jul 2005 Desktop Support Technician and Shift Supervisor First and Second tier technical support.